[Music]
this course topology and geometry the
name is not important topology and
geometry course has three main messages
so I shall State them now and I'll
repeat those three messages at the end
of the course in 3 weeks
time the but these these three messages
can be Amalgamated put together into a
single one if you can't remember three
if you want to remember just one the
message is the importance of
pictures usefulness of pictures throw
pictures use pictures work with pictures
pictures pictures pictures the entire
course is in fact
a pretext an occasion for you to start
drawing
pictures as I go around the world I meet
lots and lots of people some of them
strange some of them normal and most of
them have the impression when I tell
them that I'm a
mathematician that
mathematicians what do they do they add
or multiply B bigger and bigger numbers
faster and
[Music]
faster or if they have sophisticated a
little it they say oh
mathematicians write more and more
complicated formulas and calculate with
more and more complicated
formulas this misunderstanding is quite
common even among season
scientists you know you'll hear from now
on for the rest of your career often
people say physicist Engineers
biologists what have you say oh you do
the mathematics by which they mean
do numbers or formulas but I'd like to
convince you that there is so much more
to mathematics than numbers and formulas
people think mathematics is about
numbers and formulas but that's a
misunderstanding it's not the Mis only a
misunderstanding it is a gross
misunderstanding you see numbers
formulas of course are very important
they're useful to us but they're useful
to us in the following
sense please imagine a world where we
cannot hear we are all death we have no
acoustic yeah in this world where we
cannot hear can music
develop well people are saying No but
here is a very beautiful piece of music
composed by Mozart over the not F the
mar figuro and if you are very competent
person technically competent in music
you can read this and enjoy this
music you understand what's going
on if you are very very technically
competent maybe some of you play the
piano and other instruments maybe you
can read this by the way who can who who
plays music on here
bana
bana okay so some people even Among Us
can read this and I also have some
friends personal friends who carry
around um nowadays on the laptop or
whatever scores of Music something like
this and just open it and enjoy it by
reading
it but okay so that's ridiculous but you
can imagine that that's possible right
that's humanly possible there are people
who can do this okay now that's a little
like working in mathematics with numbers
and formulas because in the world of
mathematics we don't have
here it turns out we somehow we are all
deaf in mathematics when we are born but
by learning mathematics in the proper
way through formalism formulas numbers
and so on through all those strange
theorems and reasonings and so on
somehow other we start wanting to listen
to the real music Beyond this otherwise
all we spend doing the rest of our lives
is just write this write this and copy
this copy this copy this copy this
without hearing the actual sound am I
getting my message across yes okay so I
want you to become able to do
mathematics
not like this of course this is
important because that's the only way we
can learn mathematics we can s do
mathematics but you want I want you to
become able to hear can you say
this you
[Music]
[Applause]
this
you can stop it can stop
it that's what this
means yeah and behind numbers and
formulas in mathematics there's
something like this and that's the
pictures when you do geometry you start
not hearing but seeing mathematics like
this I want you to become able to do
this okay
okay can you switch
and so
and lights on
this so
the
three
messages of this
geometry
course so number one is that there is so
much
more in
mathematics the numbers and
formulas I again numbers and formulas
are important just as that technical
stuff is important in music if you lived
in the world of no sound because that's
the only way you would be able to access
appreciate moart
Overture but there's something
else yeah for
example there is what you might call
pictorial thinking you should
be you should start thinking
pictures
okay so here you should
think actual music ver it
is
School number two which is very much
connect Ed with this is from now on
since you had The Misfortune to meet
me please always draw
pictures
whenever you work on mathematics
now these pictures can be drawn not only
on a sheet of paper or on a
Blackboard but in your
head or on a napkin or on a sand on a
beach anywhere but please draw
pictures
always draw
pictures why is this you see there is
something unfortunate about our
educational system and I don't just mean
your individual countries where you come
from in Africa but all over the world
something very unfortunate and that
unfortunate thing is that in
mathematical
education we have been all
bullied into thinking that pictures are
not
rigorous you have probably heard this
pictur is not rigorous that you can't
trust the pictures yeah you you should
say everything in words and so
on
well sometimes Pi you can make mistakes
in pictures but just as well you can
make mistakes in words in formulas and
in calculations I would say most of the
time pictures are far more rigorous than
words and
formulas that's because we as human
beings evolved we are conditioned as
biological creatures to be very
sensitive
with high resolution to
pictures that's where we take in most of
our information our brain does it yeah a
large fraction of our brains are devoted
to processing visual
information only a small part is devoted
to left over to linguistic and
calculational things most of it is
Vision so for example if you have two
pictures and they're slightly different
you can see immediately ah they are
different right but if you have two full
pages of sentences and they're slightly
different you cannot tell the
difference you see we have much higher
much higher resolution much better
capability of
search with pictures than with anything
else similarly I've been enjoying
looking at the list of your
photographs yeah it's amazing how people
have changed
nonetheless most of us can recognize
who's
who yeah that's an amazing ability of
the human brains try to ask computer to
do
this it will flun out completely you
know if somebody has changed as um as
much
as um who has changed a lot in my
opinion
as uh for example my friend uh um I
would say
ishma we met anyway but we can process
all that information you see how
powerful human brains are in
Vision so what I'm saying is that if
you're going to be successful as
mathematical scientists wherever you go
it's completely crazy not to use Vision
because that's the best tool you have
that's the strongest and most powerful
weapon you have and if you are doing
mathematics without drawing pictures and
I shall explain what by pictures I mean
but without pictures you're doing
mathematics like this all the
time yeah well if you want to give
yourself a handicap a huge handc go
ahead others will be much happier
because you know there's less that much
less competition but you should always
draw pictures and help yourself draw
pictures draw pictures that's what you
really best at and remember when you are
little children you all love to draw
pictures at some point people said oh
you shouldn't be drawing pictures I'd
like to tell you today that the best
professional mathematical scientists
draw pictures work with the pictures
think in pictures you should become one
of
us okay finally what do I mean by
pictures by pictures sometimes we think
something like this or computer Graphics
but in fact I'd like to say that there
is so much
more to
pictures than say photos photogra
photographs of physical
objects you'll see in this course and
from now on that when I draw a picture
the picture in question does not
necessarily
represent a physical
object like
this it to be some abstract picture it
to be a picture of some logical
situation it would be a picture of some
argument it will be a picture of
something that you can only imagine but
not touch
those are the pictures that we want to
learn to draw to use and to manipulate
and to exploit
so apart from the those physical
pictures in topology and
geometry Beyond those pictures physical
pictures
geometry you should
learn to
to see
things that cannot be seen
physically in other words you are
expanding your
vision
and and to work with
by work I mean not only do you imagine
these things but you can manipulate you
can look at this from and then you can
reason on them so maybe instead of work
I should say reason on them
okay those are the three
messages and for example you might ask
what's a good concrete example remember
those mov strip
experiments we did it together with
physical objects but by the end of this
course I want you to develop enough
habit enough imagination and enough
technical competence to be able to do
all those experiments in your head and
see what happens when you take a movie
strip with one twist and cut it along
the center line and I can see ah so it's
going to be twisted this way Twisted so
it's going to be connected it will be a
one single long strip how many twists o
that's difficult to calculate but let's
see and so forth and if I cut it along
one/ third line ah so now it's going to
fall into two parts because this bit is
going to connect to this bit and the
middle one is going to be left over on
the narrower but these two will be
linked and so on yeah I want you to
become if not at the end of this course
but in the long run to become able to do
this and that you agree will make you a
much more powerful mathematical
scientist so this is what the course is
about draw pictures dra dra pictures
draw pictures as a guide guideline when
I do research in any area I have done
research in fluid mechanics I've done
research in a little bit of geometry and
dynamical systems and topology and so on
certainly geometric subjects but also
sometimes combinatorics sometimes
representation Theory and so on I always
draw pictures when I'm doing research I
would say I'm drawing one picture every
few minutes
so by the end of the day after maybe six
or seven hours I have maybe 30 40
pictures if not more so in a week that's
hundreds so by the end of this uh course
you should be drawing lots and lots of
pictures trying lots of pictures some of
these pictures later on can be in your
head but you should start by drawing
lots of real pictures on paper and I I
can come and discuss those pictures if
you like but not a few
pictures not tens of pictures but
hundreds of pictures
please
hundreds because that's how we can
eventually listen to moz's music but in
mathematics okay good okay so this is
the end of my Spiel and my speech um
thank you very much for your attention
um what do we do now it's now four
15 and are we supposed to have this
class until what
5:30 huh 515 surely that's too much so I
suggest that we do the following thing
um in each day we are supposed to have
two hours but I'm going to usually
lecture draw lots of pictures for 1 hour
and then we have a
break and after the break we'll be um
devoting the whole time to working
through exercises drawing projects I'll
give you some projects that you can
explore drawing some of you might go
through them faster some of them might
enjoy them slower that's fine and I and
the tutors will go around and helping
them and so forth and we see where we
get to by the end of the hour okay so
let's take another 5 minute break and
after the break we shall start on the
first um drawing assignment
okay and tomorrow I'll begin my lecture
course